Hello everyone, and welcome to today's session
大家好，欢迎来到今天的分享，
where I will explain how to utilize
我将解释如何利用
the natural language processing technology of Python
Python 的自然语言处理技术，
to achieve office automation tailored for translation tasks.
来实现专为翻译任务定制的办公自动化
I have carefully read through the questionnaires submitted by all of you,
大家提交的问卷我都仔细看过了，
and I have customized today's content based on your backgrounds.
今天的分享内容也是根据各位的背景专门定制的
So please listen carefully
所以请大家认真听，
as this directly addresses the pain points you mentioned.
因为这直接解决了你们提到的痛点
I noticed that the vast majority of you are master's degree students,
我注意到在座绝大多数都是硕士生，
currently facing significant pressure regarding your academic research,
目前科研压力比较大，
and you are very concerned about corpus processing and academic writing.
也非常关心语料库处理和学术写作
Many of you might wonder why we still need to learn Python
很多人可能会纳闷：咱们为啥还要学 Python，
when AI tools are already so powerful.
现在的 AI 工具不都已经这么强了吗？
The answer lies in the specific feedback you provided,
答案就在大家的反馈里
where many mentioned that AI often produces hallucinations
许多人提到，AI 经常“产生幻觉”、瞎编术语，
and you dare not use it directly.
根本不敢直接拿来用
You also mentioned the frustration of AI having character limits,
大家还提到了一个痛点，就是 AI 有字数限制，
which makes it impossible to process thousands of documents at once.
没法一次性处理几千个文档
This is where Python comes in, as it allows us to bridge the gap
这正是 Python 的用武之地，它能打通壁垒，
by connecting AI with the local files
通过连接 AI 和本地文件，
to handle massive amounts of data without limits.
无限制地批量处理海量数据
I see from the data that almost everyone is using Windows 10 or 11.
我看了一下数据，几乎所有人都在用 Windows 10 或 11
However, we do have students using Mac,
不过也有几位同学用的是 Mac，
so I will explain the Windows setup primarily, but point out differences.
所以我主要演示 Windows 设置，但也会指出区别
Regarding your technical background,
关于技术基础，
I noticed about half of you felt unsure about absolute file paths.
我注意到有一半同学对“绝对文件路径”心里没底
Please do not worry about this, we will not dive into complex concepts,
大家千万别担心，我们不讲复杂的概念，
but rather focus on practical solutions that work
而是专注于解决实际问题，
regardless of where you save your files.
不管你的文件存在哪儿都能搞定
The survey also highlighted your biggest headaches in translation work,
问卷还反映了大家翻译工作中最头疼的问题，
and we are going to solve them today.
我们今天就来一一解决
The number one problem was processing PDF files
排名第一的问题就是处理 PDF，
full of unwanted hard return line breaks and messy headers.
里面全是多余的硬回车和乱七八糟的页眉
which you currently delete manually.
大家现在只能手动删除
We will write a script to fix that instantly.
我们会写个脚本，瞬间搞定这个问题
Another major issue was the need to manually align texts
另一个大问题是需要手动对齐文本，
to create TMX translation memory files,
来制作 TMX 翻译记忆库，
and the tedious work of copying and pasting.
复制粘贴的工作量太大了
We will look at how Python can automate these repetitive actions
咱们来看看 Python 怎么自动化这些重复操作，
to save you hours of work.
帮你省下好几个小时
I also want to address the fear of coding that some of you expressed.
我还想聊聊部分同学表达的“代码恐惧症”
Many stated that if you see red error text,
很多人说，一看到屏幕上飘红报错，
your instinct is to close the software or wait for help.
第一反应就是关软件或者等人来救
I want to reassure you that our goal today is not to memorize syntax,
我想给大家吃颗定心丸：今天的目标不是背语法，
but to teach you how to write prompts that command AI to write code,
而是教你写 Prompt（提示词）指挥 AI 写代码，
and crucially, how to ask AI to fix those red errors.
最重要的是，教你怎么让 AI 去修那些报错
For those who just want a one-click tool without learning principles,
如果有同学只想要个“一键式”工具，
we will provide packaged scripts.
我们也会提供封装好的脚本
But I encourage you to understand the logic to customize them.
但我还是鼓励大家理解背后的逻辑，方便以后定制
Now let us look at the environment configuration.
好，现在我们来看看环境配置
Since most of you are on Windows, we need to ensure permissions.
因为大多数人用的都是 Windows，得先确保有权限
I see that most of you have administrator rights,
我看大部分人都有管理员权限，
which is excellent news for Windows users.
这对 Windows 用户来说是个好消息
You will need to open PowerShell as an administrator
你需要以管理员身份打开 PowerShell，
and change your execution policy to RemoteSigned.
把执行策略改成 RemoteSigned
Your terminal commands will be slightly different using source on Mac,
Mac 用户激活环境的命令会稍微不一样，
and I have included specific notes in the PDF regarding network issues.
具体的注意事项和网络问题解决方法，我都写在 PDF 里了
Some of you mentioned that accessing foreign websites can be slow.
有些同学提到访问国外网站很慢
To solve this, we will use a tool
为了解决这个问题，我们会用一个工具，
which speeds up downloads by using optimized mirrors.
通过国内镜像源来加速下载
So you do not need to worry about your network speed.
所以大家不用担心网速问题
We will be installing libraries like pandas for data processing,
我们会安装大家感兴趣的库，比如做数据的 pandas，
and NLTK for text analysis,
做文本分析的 NLTK，
and even some automation tools for RPA.
甚至还有给感兴趣的同学准备的 RPA 自动化工具
Finally, regarding the learning materials,
最后是关于学习资料
many requested video replays and PDF tutorials to review at your own pace.
很多人想要视频回放和 PDF 教程，方便按自己的节奏复习
We have prepared all of these materials, including a setup guide.
这些我们都准备好了，包括一份环境配置指南
so you can focus on listening now and practice later.
所以现在大家可以专心听，回头再上手练习
There is a fundamental difference between enterprise and personal development.
企业级开发和个人提效开发，有着本质的区别
Enterprise development focuses on architecture and security,
企业开发讲究架构、安全，
which belongs to the work of professional programmers.
那是专业程序员的事
Personal efficiency development focuses on speed and being lightweight.
而个人提效开发，讲究的是“快”和“轻”
So our learning goal is not to write perfect software,
所以我们的目标不是写出完美的软件，
but to use just a few dozen lines of code to solve repetitive operations.
而是用几十行代码解决那些机械重复的操作
Various AI tools and traditional office software are just isolated tools,
各种 AI 工具和办公软件往往是孤立的，
whereas the core value of Python is acting as the glue
而 Python 的核心价值就是做“胶水”，
that connects AI, documents and databases to build your workflow.
把 AI、文档和数据库连起来，构建你的工作流
This specifically solves the two core pain points in translation:
这能专门解决翻译工作的两个核心痛点：
data cleaning and format layout.
数据清洗和格式排版
Next, I will share two core application cases of Python.
接下来，我分享两个 Python 的核心应用案例
The first case is making bilingual comparison tables.
第一个案例是制作双语对照表
In our work, we often encounter long documents listed one above the other.
我们经常遇到原文和译文上下排列的长文档，
and we need to turn them into a side by side table format.
我们需要把它转成左右对照的表格形式
Manually copying and pasting is extremely inefficient,
手动复制粘贴效率极低，
and AI processing has limits on the amount of text input.
而 AI 又有输入字数限制
However Python can read text without limits and distinguish lines.
但 Python 可以无限制读取文本，自动区分原文和译文
Using pandas, it can export to Excel with one click
利用 pandas，我们可以一键导出 Excel，
or directly generate a Word document with formatting,
或者直接生成排好格式的 Word 文档，
so no manual adjustment is needed.
完全不需要手动调格式
Imagine this program as a smart assistant helping you organize work.
你可以把这个程序想象成一个帮你整理稿件的智能助手
Its goal is to take a text file where sentences are mixed
它的任务就是把中英文混排的文本文件
and convert it into a table.
转换成表格
The process starts with a setup phase.
过程从设置阶段开始
The code first collects the necessary digital tools.
代码首先会调用所需的数字工具
After getting its tools ready, the program acts like a detective,
准备好后，程序就像个侦探，
it scans the folder you are currently working in.
扫描你当前工作的文件夹
It is looking for a text file with "bilingual" in its name.
寻找文件名包含“bilingual”（双语）的文本文件
If it finds the file, it picks it up to start working.
一旦找到，就开始干活
If it searches and finds nothing, it does not crash.
如果啥也没找到，它也不会崩溃，
Instead it automatically creates a small sample file for you.
而是会自动给你生成一个示例文件
This ensures that the process always has something to work on.
这确保了程序总有东西可跑
Once the file is ready, the core processing begins.
文件就绪后，核心处理就开始了
Think of this part as a sorting machine.
把这部分想象成一台分拣机
The program reads the text file line by line.
程序逐行读取文本
It ignores any empty space to keep things clean.
它会忽略空行以保持整洁，
It performs a check: does this line contain Chinese?
然后检查：这一行包含中文吗？
If yes, it throws that line into a pile labeled Chinese.
如果是，就丢进“中文”堆里
If no, it throws that line into a pile labeled English.
如果不是，就丢进“英文”堆里
After separating, the program aligns them side by side.
分好类后，程序会把它们并排对齐
It creates a spreadsheet with English and Chinese columns.
生成一个含中英文两列的电子表格
It looks at the clock to see the exact current time.
它还会看一眼时钟，获取当前精确时间
It adds this time to the file name to avoid overwriting.
把时间加到文件名里，防止覆盖旧文件
This spreadsheet is then saved to your computer.
然后，这个表格会保存到你的电脑上
The final step is about making the result look beautiful.
最后一步是美化
The program opens a blank word document and draws a table.
程序打开一个空白 Word，画一个表格
It fills the table with your sorted text.
把分拣好的文本填进去
It goes one step further by acting like a typesetter.
它甚至像个排版工：
It changes the English text to a standard professional style,
把英文设成标准的专业字体，
and sets the Chinese text to a font good for Asian characters.
把中文设成适合亚洲字符的字体
It saves this final polished document for you.
最后保存这个排版精美的文件
You start with a simple text file, and this automation does the heavy lifting
你只需提供一个简单文本，自动化搞定繁重工作，
giving you a perfect Excel and Word without copying and pasting.
直接拿走完美的表格和文档，一次复制粘贴都不用
The second case is batch processing of scanned PDF files.
第二个案例是批量处理扫描版 PDF
Python can go through a folder containing all your PDF files,
Python 可以遍历文件夹里的 PDF，
call upon AI interfaces like Baidu or Alibaba Cloud for OCR.
调用百度或阿里云等接口进行文字识别
We can also use multithreading to increase recognition speed.
我们还能用多线程技术来提升速度
Please note that some AI interfaces have query limits per second.
注意，有些 AI 接口限制每秒查询次数
You can choose an interface with looser limits,
你可以选限制宽松的接口，
or add a delay function to avoid being blocked.
或者加个延迟，免得被服务器屏蔽
If you are processing confidential files like contracts,
如果处理合同这类保密文件，
you can download free offline models to your local computer.
可以下载免费的离线模型到本地
Processing locally without uploading ensures data security.
本地处理不上传，确保数据安全
This project acts like a highly intelligent Digital Research Assistant.
这个项目就像一个高智商的科研助手
Its job is to read through complex academic PDF files
它的工作是通读复杂的学术 PDF，
and automatically extract important technical terms.
自动提取重要的技术术语
Imagine you have a dense scientific paper
想象你有一篇密集的科技论文，
and want a glossary without reading every sentence.
想不读全文就整理出一份术语表
This program does exactly that using advanced filters.
这个程序利用高级过滤器就能帮你搞定
The process begins with a preparation phase.
流程从准备阶段开始
The computer gathers necessary tools and dictionaries.
计算机先加载必要的工具和词典
to understand human text.
以理解人类文本
Once loaded, the program downloads the PDF to analyze.
加载后，程序读取你要分析的 PDF
It acts like a very careful reader.
它像个非常细心的读者
It opens the file and fixes common formatting errors.
打开文件，修复常见的格式错误
For example, stitching words split by hyphens.
比如，拼好被连字符切断的单词
It also scrubs away distraction marks like citations,
它还会擦除引文标记等干扰项，
so it can focus purely on the words.
只专注于文字本身
After cleaning, it moves to finding potential terms.
清洗完，就开始寻找潜在术语
It uses linguistic rules to look for specific patterns.
它利用语言学规则查找特定模式
It specifically hunts for noun phrases where technical terms live.
专门搜寻技术术语所在的“名词短语”
For example, combinations like "artificial intelligence".
比如“人工智能”这样的组合
At the same time, it acts like a security guard with a blacklist.
同时，它又像个拿着黑名单的保安
It automatically rejects generic academic fluff words,
自动拦截通用的学术“水词”
like "figure" or "conclusion", as they are not technical terms.
像“图表”或“结论”，这些都不是技术术语
It filters thousands of useless words to ensure quality.
它过滤掉成千上万个无用词，确保质量
Once it has a list, the program acts like a judge.
有了列表后，程序变身成法官
It uses a scoring system to decide word importance.
利用评分系统裁决单词重要性
It counts frequency and checks uniqueness to the document.
计算词频，并检查该词的独特性
It also performs a smart cleanup, merging similar terms.
它还会智能清理，合并相似的词
like "method" and "methods".
比如单复数形式
It removes shorter terms already part of better long terms.
删除已包含在长术语中的短词，避免重复
Finally, the program organizes the winning terms.
最后，程序组织这些“赢家”词汇
sorting them by their importance score.
按重要性得分排序
It even grabs a snippet of the original text for context.
它甚至会抓取一小段原文作为上下文
It saves all this into a neat spreadsheet.
所有信息保存到一个整洁的表格里
You end up with a clean professional glossary.
你最终得到一份干净、专业的术语表
including the term, translation space, and importance score.
包含术语、翻译栏和重要性分数
I also want to clarify why we still need traditional NLP methods.
我也想解释一下，为啥还需要学传统 NLP 方法
Even though AI capabilities are strong.
尽管现在的 AI 能力很强
AI can have hallucinations and is not always controllable,
但 AI 会有幻觉，结果不可控，
whereas traditional logic is more precise in data extraction.
而传统逻辑在数据提取上更精确
After obtaining text through OCR,
通过 OCR 获取文本后，
we can use traditional methods for word division and tagging.
我们可以用传统方法进行分词和标注
We can also automatically extract entities,
我们还可以自动提取实体，
such as names, organizations, time, and amounts.
比如人名、机构、时间和金额
This applies directly to building professional databases.
这能直接用于构建专业数据库
like scanning contracts to extract names and amounts.
比如扫描合同，提取名称和金额
generating an Excel file.
生成 Excel 文件
Processing large files takes only about 10 seconds,
处理大文件也只要 10 秒左右，
far more efficient than manual work.
效率远超人工
I have also demonstrated the results of the classic paper.
我还演示了那篇经典论文的结果
"Attention is all you need"
也就是《Attention is all you need》
I will share the code, but first you need to configure Python.
我会分享代码，但得先配好 Python 环境
For zero foundation students, I will organize the process in detail.
针对零基础同学，我会详细梳理流程
Now I will explain the basic configuration for Windows.
现在来讲讲 Windows 的基本配置
since the survey showed that is what most of you use.
因为调查显示大家都用这个
Mac devices are basically the same, with few command differences.
Mac 操作基本一致，只有少数命令不同
Students who can't keep up can view the document later.
跟不上的同学可以稍后查看文档
First, download Python from the official website.
第一步，去官网下载 Python
I recommend version 3.12 or 3.13.
建议选 3.12 或 3.13 版本
not too new to avoid issues, nor too old for security.
避开太新或太旧的版本，确保兼容和安全
When installing on Windows, check "Add Python to Path".
安装时一定要勾选 "Add Python to PATH"
to avoid manually configuring variables later.
免得以后手动配变量
Second step is specifically for Windows.
第二步是 Windows 特有的
Search for PowerShell, run as administrator.
搜索 PowerShell，以管理员身份运行
and input the command "Get-ExecutionPolicy".
输入命令 `Get-ExecutionPolicy`
If it shows restricted, input "Set-ExecutionPolicy RemoteSigned".
如果受限，输入 `Set-ExecutionPolicy RemoteSigned`
Press Y to confirm unlocking permissions.
按 Y 确认解锁权限
Third step, choose an editor like VS Code, PyCharm or Cursor.
第三步，选个编辑器，比如 VS Code、PyCharm 或 Cursor
Just choose according to your needs.
大家按需选择就行
Fourth step is configuring a virtual environment.
第四步配置虚拟环境
Do not let all projects use the same environment.
千万别混用环境，
I suggest establishing an independent one for each project.
建议为每个项目建立独立环境
Windows inputs creation and activation commands.
Windows 输入创建激活命令
Mac inputs "source venv/bin/activate".
Mac 输入 `source venv/bin/activate`
Fifth step is installing libraries using "pip install".
第五步用 `pip install` 安装库
I recommend installing "uv" tool first to speed up.
建议先装 "uv" 工具来加速
Then use "uv pip install" for pandas, NLTK and SciPy.
然后用 `uv pip install` 安装 pandas 等库
After configuration, do not memorize code.
配好后，不用死记硬背
You can use AI to assist in generating Python scripts.
可以用 AI 辅助生成脚本
For simple needs, use natural language to describe requirements.
简单的需求，直接用大白话描述
like "read PDF, extract numbers and terms, and save".
比如“读 PDF，提取数字和术语，并保存”
asking it to write a Python script for you.
让它帮你写脚本
For complex projects, learn professional prompt templates.
复杂项目可以学点专业 Prompt
to let AI generate code that better fits your needs.
让代码更符合需求
Simply copy the AI code into your editor to run.
复制粘贴代码运行即可
Python is not for rote memorization,
Python 不是用来死记硬背的，
but a tool unlocking office software functions.
而是解锁办公软件功能的工具
Once mastered, it links local files and AI,
学会后，联动本地文件和 AI，
improving work efficiency.
提升工作效率
All processes are in the document shared in the group.
所有流程文档都在群里
Next is Q&A time.
接下来是问答环节
Turn on mic to ask or screen share for problems.
可以开麦提问或共享屏幕
I will display slides for Python installation steps.
我会投屏演示安装步骤
If no questions, this course ends here.
没问题的话，今天就到这里
Welcome to exchange ideas anytime later.
欢迎随时交流